<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles exhibited against the King, and the charge of the Army, against His Majesty; drawn up by the Generall Councell of Officers, for the speedy executing of impartiall justice upon his person; and the time, place, and manner of his tryall. Also, a message to His Majesty concerning the same; and his declaration and proposals touching the Crown of England, and the government thereof; and the resolution of the Army in order thereunto. Likewise, the declaration of the citizens of London, concerning the tryall of the King; and proposals to the Lord Gen. Fairfax, for liberty and freedom. With a joyfull and satisfactory answer thereunto.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E536_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205340</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 83:E536[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles exhibited against the King, and the charge of the Army, against His Majesty; drawn up by the Generall Councell of Officers, for the speedy executing of impartiall justice upon his person; and the time, place, and manner of his tryall. Also, a message to His Majesty concerning the same; and his declaration and proposals touching the Crown of England, and the government thereof; and the resolution of the Army in order thereunto. Likewise, the declaration of the citizens of London, concerning the tryall of the King; and proposals to the Lord Gen. Fairfax, for liberty and freedom. With a joyfull and satisfactory answer thereunto.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Gilbert, neer Temple-Bar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 29.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army. --  Council --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116980:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES Exhibited againſt the KING, <hi>AND</hi> The CHARGE of the Army, againſt His Majeſty; Drawn up by the Generall Councell of Officers, for the ſpeedy executing of impartiall Juſtice upon His Perſon; and the time, place, and manner of His Tryall.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A Meſſage to His Majeſty concerning the ſame; And His Declaration and Propoſals touching the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and the Government thereof; and the Reſolution of the Army in order thereunto.</p>
            <p>LIKEWISE, The Declaration of the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> concerning the Tryall of the King; And Propoſals to the Lord Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> for Liberty and Freedom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVith a joyfull and ſatisfactory Anſwer thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Gilbert,</hi> neer Temple-Bar, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:116980:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116980:2"/>
            <head>The gallant RESOLVTION Of the Lord Generall FAIRFAX Concerning The ſpeedy re-inveſting of His Majeſties Royall Perſon, the time appointed, and the manner how He ſhall be eſtabliſhed: With the Propoſals of the Army, for the preſent ſetling of the peace of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Excellency the Lord Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> Lieuten. General <hi>Crumwell</hi> and the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Officers, have ſeriouſly debated the Remonſtrance and Propoſals of the Army, for the ſpeedy ſetling of the peace of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116980:3"/>and executing of impartiall Juſtice upon all Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whatſoever; and to that end, have drawn up a Charge againſt the King, which containeth theſe particulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That <hi>Charles Steward</hi> hath acted contrary to his truſt, in departing from the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That the ſaid <hi>Charles Steward</hi> hath forfeited his truſt repoſed in him by the people, by ſetting up his Standard, making a war againſt them, and thereby been occaſion of much bloudſhed and miſery to the people whom hee was ſet over for good.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That the ſaid <hi>Charles Steward</hi> hath been the chiefe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of augmenting and promoting a ſecond War, by granting Commiſſions to Incendiaries and Malignants, and inviting them thereunto.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the ſaid <hi>Charles Steward</hi> hath acted contrary to the Liberties of the Subject, and tending to the deſtruction of the fundamentall Laws and Liberties of this <hi>Kingdome;</hi> all which amounts to a forfeiture of the ſaid truſt repoſed in him by the People at his Coronation, with much more to this effect.</p>
            <p>The Councel of War (who now manage buſineſſe, as in relation to him have to ordered the way of State and Majeſty obſerved about him, as to perſons and manner, <hi>viz.</hi> that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be done upon the knee, in reference to his tryall, who (as is ſaid) will receive it at <hi>Windſor</hi> about the 6. day of the next moneth. And it is ſaid, that his Maj. upon the receipt hereof, declated, That though he could have no reſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his right, priviledges, and Crown, and had participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of far more trouble and miſery in this world, than any of his (late) Predeceſors, yet he doubted not, but in the world to come, to receive an everlaſting Crown of glory.</p>
            <div type="proposals">
               <pb facs="tcp:116980:3"/>
               <head>His Majesties Propoſals touching the Crown of England.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, That no Law can judge a King, or make him rightly to ſuffer death by any power. 2 That though Hee ſuffers under them by reſtraint, yet his Iriſh Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects will come in their time and reſcue Him. 3 That all men when they find that great decay of trade, which will be, if the Kingdome be not ſetled by him, they will reſcue him. 4 That He knowes what an influence is from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upo him; That, that if he be not reſtored, they will not be ſatisfied. 5 That the kingdome is generally well pleaſed with what he condeſcended to, as very great on his part, at the Treaty with the Parliament. 6 That the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> are of great power both in purſe and ſtrength, and will oppoſe any that ſhall ſeek to deſtroy him. 7 That reliefe will come to him from ſeverall parts of Chriſtendome. 8 That his Sonne Prince <hi>Charles</hi> is able to raiſe a good ſtrength in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1 That there is not only example hereof in other parts, but in <hi>Scotland,</hi> yea, and <hi>England</hi> alſo, of the 35 laſt Kings, above twenty were impoſed and depoſed by power. 2 That nothing will ruine his Majeſty more, than joyning with the Iriſh againſt his Proteſtant Subjects. 3 That there will be a ſudden courſe taken for ſetling of trade, and inriching the kingdome. 4 That Law and Juſtice being executed, it will render great ſatisfaction to the people. 5. That the kingdom cannot be ſatisfied with <hi>Ormonds</hi> negotation with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in <hi>Ireland.</hi> 6 That the City of <hi>London</hi> will bee new modelled, and begins to be framed to a pretty good order, and temper, ſince the putting of Malignants our of power and authority. 7 That forreign forces cannot daunt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Souldiery of <hi>England.</hi> 8 That the French have troubles enough at home, by the preſent diſtractions in the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> and that the Prince wants money for facilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his deſign in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <pb facs="tcp:116980:4"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>ON Saturday laſt his Majeſty arrived, being guarded by Coly <hi>Hariſon,</hi> and ten Troops of Horſe, who upon their coming, a great influence of people reſorted to the Townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, and upon his Majeſties paſſing by, a great eccho aroſe, from the voyce of the people, crying, <hi>God bleſſe your Majeſty and ſend you long to reign.</hi> And after that his Royal perſon were conducted to the Caſtle, and the dark Curtain from the Canopy of Heaven being drawn, the Royalits (in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places throughout the town) began to drink a carouſe to their dread Soveraign; but with an Eagles Eye being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, they were ſoon taken off from that Ceremonial and Court-like action; for notice thereof being given to the Capt. of the Guard, ſeveral ſides of muſquetiers were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded forth for the ſecuring of them, but upon their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance towards the place of ſanctuary, they found <hi>Bacchus</hi> in the poſture of <hi>Mars</hi> to receive them, the Royaliſts ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in a poſture of defence, and would not give admittance: whereupon, the Soldiery forced their paſſage, broke in upon them, wounded divers, killed three, and ſecured the reſt, who are now committed to ſafe cuſtody, to anſwer their high in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and commotion before a Councel of War.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>VVindſor</hi> 
                           <date>28. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1648.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And Letters further from <hi>Windſor</hi> intimates, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is very pleaſant and meery, ſince his comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and takes much delight in diſputing the caſe of the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: further purporting, that his Maj. is determined to draw up a Meſſage to be ſent to the Lord Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> by way of gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulation, for his preſent accommodation, and that He may be admitted to London, to confer with his Excellency about ſome things of weighty importance, in relation to the unanimous eſtabliſhing of his bleeding Kingdoms, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to make future proviſion for the Souldiery, and to give all due and lawfull ſatisfaction in all things deſired by the Army.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116980:4"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Decemb.</hi> 26. Letters from the Navy ſay, That there hath bin a bloudy Fight at Sea between the Engliſh &amp; the Iriſh, and thta the Iriſh have obtained the Conqueſt, and taken 14 Marchants ſhips, and others, 40 piece of Ordnance, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rich booty and prize. A ſpeedy courſe will be taken for ſubduing the ſaid Rebels.</p>
                     <p>The Lord Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and Lieut Gen. <hi>Crumwell,</hi> hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Lord Admirall a viſit, where they congratulated each others good ſucceſſes, and at a Conference, profeſſed joynt concurrence, in what might make the kingdome hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: ſome diſputation hapned, in reference to the King, and ſetling of the Kingdom.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="remonstrance">
               <head>A Remonstrance from Glouceſter-ſhire.</head>
               <p n="1">1 We do ſeriouſly profeſs, that though your former proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt that Generation were exceedingly proſpered, beyond the parallell of former ages, and had engraven upon them the kindneſſe of God to a diſtreſſed people; yet they had but ſerved to make us more exquiſitly miſerable, if your former Conqueſts ſhould have acquieſced in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that Houſe; who were bringing your conquered pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner with honour and ſafety to ſit upon his Throne of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, Majeſty, and Greatneſſe, without ſatisfaction for the bloud that hath been ſpilt both by Sea and Land, or ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent proviſion made for the ſecurity of the liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 We were filled with ſorrow when we ſaw the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Apoſtacy, and degenerated actings of the majority of the Houſe of Commons, who after we had bought their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity with our moſt precious bloud and treaſure, ſhould by treating with the King, ſo cruelly ſell us into the bloud and revenge of him, and his confederats, ſo contrary to their firſt principles and Declarations; the conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116980:5"/>as it filled us with amazement, ſo it drew from us thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a mutual Remonſtrance, to live and dy, and ſtand and fall with your Excellency, for the eſtabliſhing of peace and righteouſneſſe, in our native, bleeding, and languiſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>The well affected party within the City of <hi>London,</hi> have declared their unanimous reſolutions, to live and die with the Army, in the ſpeedy and impartial executing of Juſtice, upon the grand Delinquents of this Kingdom, which is wel taken and reſcented by the Councel of Officers.</p>
               <p>The work goes on, about the chuſing of Common coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel men, and it is ſaid, there are as many ſoldiers made choiſe of, as may almoſt ſerve for a Councel of War.</p>
               <p>Yeſterday 16 of the reſtrained members were ſent for to the Gen. quarters, and told, that if they would promiſe to act nothing againſt the army, they might have their liberty: whereupon they deſired, 1 To know if that was the Generals pleaſure, 2 To know if they might not have their liberty without any engagement, and it was permitted them, their names are, Lord <hi>Weinman,</hi> Sir <hi>VValter Earl,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Pye,</hi> Sir <hi>Samule Luke,</hi> Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Somes,</hi> and the reſt. As for the fore-going Charge againſt the King, it is ſaid, the army are reſolved to try him very ſpeedily, and that if he can acquit himſelf of the guilt thereof, that then hee ſhall be re-inveſted, and reſtored to his juſt Rights and Dignities.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116980:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
